A Guide to the Fred C. Galle Papers 1901-1998
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Fred C. Galle Papers 1901-1998
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10553-ai
ca. 1,000 items (6 Hollinger boxes, ca. 2.5 linear feet)
This collection consists of the papers and records of horticulturist Fred C. Galle, ca. 1901-1998, chiefly pertaining to his study of azaleas and hollies.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library in April 1999 by Mrs. Betty N. Galle, Springfield, Illinois.
Biographical/Historical Information
Fred Charles Galle was formerly the Director of Horticulture at Callaway Gardens, Pine Mountain, Georgia, 1953-1979, and served as Curator until his retirement in August of 1983. Active in many horticultural organizations, Galle was the president of the American Rhododendron Society, 1979-1981, winning its Gold Medal Award in 1983. He has also served as a past director of the Holly Society of America, and president of both the American Association of Botanic Gardens and Arboreta and the American Horticultural Society. From 1964 until 1971, Mr. Galle served on the Advisory Council of the United States National Arboretum in Washington, D.C.
His landmark book, Azaleas, published by Timber Press in 1985, was listed by the U.S.D.A. National Agriculture Library at Beltsville, Maryland, as one of the fifty great American gardening books. Another one of his books, Hollies: the Genus Ilex, won the American Horticultural Society Book Award and, according to August E. Kehr, it is the "first authoritative and comprehensive guidebook" on hollies in the English language. Galle received his bachelor and masters degree in Horticulture from Ohio State University and did graduate work at the University of Tennessee. He was also a veteran of World War II, winning a Purple Heart, Bronze Star, and a Cluster. In 1964, Galle was elected a Fellow of The Royal Horticultural Society, London, Great Britain.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of the papers and records of horticulturist Fred C. Galle (1919-1998), chiefly pertaining to his study of azaleas and hollies, including research notes, photographs and slides, correspondence, printed and typescript articles, electrostatic copies of articles, azalea seed samples, photostatic copies of two works by botanist Ludwig Eduard Theodor Loesener (1865-1941) concerning hollies and other plants in their family, and cassette tape recordings concerning entries from an encyclopedia of the Satsuki Azalea and a text about Ludwig Eduard Theodor Loesener translated by Al Faessler (audiocassette 0020, tapes 1, 2). About a hundred years ago, Loesener wrote a two-part monograph in Latin and German on the plant family Aquifoliaceae, which includes the genera Ilex(hollies) as its largest subgroup, and was the last definitive work on hollies prior to that of Galle.
Much of this material was assembled to aid Galle in the research and writing of his book, Hollies: the Genus Ilex, and most of the earliest dated material consists of printed articles, electrostatic and photostatic copies of articles, and pages from reference books concerning hollies, azaleas, and other plants.
Correspondents found in the correspondence file concerning azaleas include: Richard Abel, John Creech, Toichi Domoto, Ted Groszkiewicz, George W. Harding, Dr. J. Heursel, August E. Kehr, Massaki Kunishige, Takeo Kuwana, David G. Leach, Jay W. Murray, W.R. Philipson, W. Schmalscheidt, Henry T. Skinner, Hideo Suzuki, and William T. Turner.
Correspondents in the holly correspondence folder include: Richard Abel, Barton M. Bauers, Sr., T.R. Dudley, Gene Eisenbeiss, Shiu-ying Hu, R.J. Hutton, Mike Lynch, Elwin R. Orton, Jr., W.J. Tancig, and Linda J. Willms.
There are also complete sets of photostatic copies of Monographia Aquifoliacearum I & II, with the Index, by Theodor Loesener, 1901 & 1908.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically under two Series: Azaleas & Miscellaneous Files, and Hollies.
Contents List
- Azaleas & Miscellaneous Files 1920-1997 (Box 1-2)
  - Articles re Azaleas (Printed) 1950-1981, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Articles re Azaleas (Typescripts) 1992, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Articles re Horticulturists & Nurseries 1972-1995 (Box 1)
  - Articles re Miscellaneous Plants 1989, 1994, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Azalea Taxonomy 1957-1981, n.d. (Box 1)
  - "Bear Facts on Gregory Bald" and Related Material 1959-1970 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence re Azaleas 1967-1997, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Henry T. Skinner re Azaleas 1982-1984, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Japanese Plant Tours 1982, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Kurume Azaleas 1920, 1961, 1974, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Native Azaleas 1940-1983, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Personal Information re Fred Galle 1964-1985 (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Azaleas 1986, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Rhododendron species Foundation Tour 1988 (Box 2)
  - Satsuki Azaleas 1971-1981, n.d., 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Slides of Azalea, including Fred Galle's azalea crosses ca. 1977-1983 (Box 2)
  - Standardization of Color Names in Horticulture 1984 & n.d. (Box 2)
- Hollies 1901-1998 (Box 2-6)
  - Abbreviations, Conversion Tables, Citations of Chinese Names, and Other Tables n.d. (Box 2)
  - Articles re Hollies (Miscellaneous) 1916, 1988-1989, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Articles re Hollies by Shiu-Ying Hu 1953-1967 (Box 2)
  - Articles re Hollies in Asia 1913-1994, n.d., 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Articles re Hollies in the Canary Islands & Madeira 1977, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Articles re Hollies in Central & South America 1919-1990, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Articles re Hollies in Europe 1988-1993 (Box 3)
  - Articles re Hollies in Great Britain ("English Hollies") 1915, 1980-1988, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Articles re Hollies in the United States 1925-1997, n.d., 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Brownell Holly Arboretum and Nursery Catalogs ca. 1954 (Box 3)
  - Classification of Holly 1942-1991 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence re Hollies 1963, 1983-1998 (Box 3)
  - "Folklore of the Hollies" by Harry William Dengler n.d. (Box 3)
  - Hollies in the Landscape 1986-1990, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Holly Breeders & Introducers 1989-1994, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Holly Fossils n.d. (Box 4)
  - Holly Glossary, Index to Common & Colloquial Names and References 1993, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Holly Plant Patents 1958-1994, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Holly Propagation and Breeding 1950-1991, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Holly Society of America 1966 (Box 4)
  - Holly Sources in the United States 1988, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Index Kewensis References to Ilex1994, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Index of Species by Sections and Series n.d. (Box 4)
  - Introduction to Cultivars and Ilex Species 1993, n.d. (Box 4)
  - List of Species in Edwin, Krussman, & Rehder 1949, 1964 (Box 4)
  - Loesener (1942) Taxa Index 1991 (Box 4)
  - Ludwig Eduard Theodor Loesener (1865-1941) 1991 (Box 5)
  - Meserve Hollies 1970-1997 (Box 5)
  - Monographia Aquifoliacearum(Photostatic Copy) by Theodor Loesener 1901, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Monographia Aquifoliacearum Index(Photostatic Copy) by Theodor Loesener 1901 (Box 5)
  - Monographia Aquifoliacearum Il(Photostatic Copy) by Theodor Loesener 1908, 1 of 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Monographia Aquifoliacearum Il(Photostatic Copy) by Theodor Loesener 1908 (Box 6)
  - Notes on Holly n.d. (Box 6)
  - Photographs & Illustrations for Hollies: the Genus Ilex by Fred Galle n.d. (Box 6)
  - Reference to be checked for the Holly book Hollies: the Genus Ilex by Fred Galle 1992, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Reviews re Hollies: The Genus Ilex by Fred Galle 1997-1998 (Box 6)
  - "The Story of Hollies" by T.R. Dudley 1986-1987 (Box 6)